John Maurice Hohlfeld Papers 1950-1972 Mss.Ms.Coll.46
American Philosophical Society
John Maurice Hohlfeld Papers
1950-1972
Mss.Ms.Coll.46
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet Ca. 500 items
The educator and linguist John Maurice Hohlfeld received his doctorate in education at the University of Pennsylvania in 1950 for a dissertation focused on the teaching of foreign languages. Throughout his career as professor of linguistics at the Kennedy School of Missions at the Hartford Theological Seminary, Hohlfeld maintained an interest in the teaching of languages, and during the 1960s, he developed an interest in the linguistics of jokes and humor. The Hohlfeld Papers consist of a small assemblage of materials related to the linguistic interests and teaching of John Maurice Hohlfeld. The most valuable materials in the collection are an assortment of student papers regarding the pedagogical materials used in teaching missionaries, including materials on three African languages, Fulani, Senoufo, and Bemba, as well as Machiguenga and Asmat. The collection also includes outlines and background materials for two works by Hohlfeld that never appeared in print, "Linguistic Structure of Jokes" and "Introduction to Applied Linguistics." The former consists of numerous jokes and comics culled by Hohlfeld from newspapers and the popular media for their linguistic implications.
Hohlfeld, John Maurice, 1909-1973
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Emma S. Hohlfeld, 1987 (accn no. 1987-39ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Hohlfeld Papers consist of a small assemblage of materials related to the linguistic interests and teaching of John Maurice Hohlfeld. The most valuable materials in the collection are an assortment of student papers regarding the pedagogical materials used in teaching missionaries, primarily in West Africa. These include materials on three African languages, Fulani, Senoufo, and Bemba, as well as Machiguenga (Peru) and Asmat (New Guinea).
The collection also includes outlines and background materials for two works by Hohlfeld that never appeared in print, "Linguistic Structure of Jokes" and "Introduction to Applied Linguistics." The former consists of numerous jokes and comics culled by Hohlfeld from newspapers and the popular media for their linguistic implications.
The folders are arranged alphabetically, using the titles supplied by Hohlfeld.
Biographical/Historical note
The educator and linguist John Maurice Hohlfeld received his doctorate in education at the University of Pennsylvania in 1950 for a dissertation focused on the teaching of foreign languages. Throughout his career as professor of linguistics at the Kennedy School of Missions at the Hartford Theological Seminary and at the University of Hartford, Hohlfeld maintained an interest in applied linguistics and the teaching of languages, and during the 1960s, he developed an interest in the linguistics of jokes and humor.
Hartford Theological Seminary; Asmat language; Bemba language; English language--Study and teaching--Foreign speakers; Fulani language; Language and languages--Study and teaching; Linguistics--United States; Machiguenga language; Senoufo language; Structural linguistics; Syllabi; Wit and humor
- John Maurice Hohlfeld Papers, 1950-1972; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - Braille ("Linguistics -- hearing, (Braille), (lip reading), listening"), 1950-1972
  - Comics, humor, jokes, 1954-1970
    Scope and Contents note
    Clippings from newspapers and magazines.
  - Communication seminar, 1953-1969
    Notes regarding seminar in communication arts and intro. to structural linguistics.
  - Etymology, 1954-1972; 2 folders
  - An experiment employing two methods of teaching Spanish to College Freshmen, 1950; 2 copies; Hohlfeld, John Maurice
    Dissertation, University of Pennsylvania.
  - Introduction to Applied Linguistics (rough draft), n.d.
  - Jokes (card file), n.d.
    Transcribed jokes of uncertain provenance.
  - Language games, 1956-1972
  - Language learning techniques, 1968-1969
  - Linguistic assistance to foreign students, 1951-1952, 1970
  - Linguistic Structure of Jokes (newspaper clippings), 1962-1969
  - Linguistic Structure of Jokes (rough draft), n.d.
  - Pedagogical materials -- Miscellaneous, 1960-1969
  - Pedagogical materials -- Student papers, 1961-1967
    - Some factors relevant to the writing of a pedagogical grammar of Bemba, 1962; Anderson, Fred R.
    - A critique of the lesson book of the Language School Mission Baptiste, Korhogo, Cote d'Ivoire, 1961; Bothel, Donald F.
    - An evaluation of my Hausa pedagogical materials, 1961; Kraft, Charles
    - Language learning techniques, 1967; Mainhood, Dorothy
    - Pedagogical materials, 1967; Mainhood, Dorothy
    - A critique of An Introduction to Haitian Creole, 1962; Orjala, Paul R.
    - Asmat language pedagogical materials, n.d.; Roessler, Calvin
    - A statement of desired additional work in language learning materials, 1967; Rogers, Miriam E.
    - Palatalized consonants and subject prefixes in Machiguenga, 1963; Snell, Betty A.
    - A sample lesson of pedagogical materials in Fulani, 1961; Stennes, Leslie H.
  - Literacy seminar, 1952
    Notes regarding seminar in adult literacy at Kennedy School of Missions, Hartford Seminary Foundation.
  - Special projects in linguistics (Lin. 840), 1969-1971
    Notes regarding seminar at Kennedy School of Missions, Hartford Seminary Foundation, including two student papers.